Finding aid for Herbert John Davis Personal papers CA.MS.00010
Smith College Archives
Herbert John Davis Personal Papers
1893-1973
Smith College Archives
Davis, Herbert John, 1893-1967.
CA.MS.00010
2.5 linear feet (6 containers)
Herbert John Davis was the fourth president of Smith College, professor of English and world-renowned expert on Jonathan Swift. This collection contains material primarily related to his personal life including correspondence, speeches, publications, photographs, newspaper articles, and memorabilia.
Biographical / Historical
Herbert John Davis was born on May 24, 1893 in Northamptonshire, England, where he received his elementary and secondary education. He later attended Oxford University (St. John's College) from which he graduated in 1914. He then served in France and Belgium during WWI and in 1919 he returned to Oxford to earn his A.M. In 1922, Davis married Gertrude Lucas of Opladen, Rheinland, Germany but she died tragically just six years later. In 1930, Davis married Gladys Wookey of Toronto and the couple had two daughters, Charlotte Elisabeth Ann and Jane.
In 1920, Davis acquired a position at the University of Leeds where he taught for two years. He then moved to the University of Toronto where he remained for sixteen years. Davis was hired as an Associate Professor of English, and later promoted to a full Professor. He also served as chair of the English department. In 1938, Davis accepted a position as chair of the English department at Cornell University.
In 1939, Davis succeeded William Allan Neilson as president of Smith College and he assumed this role for the 1940-1941 school year. Davis served as the fourth president of Smith College until 1949 when he returned to Oxford as a reader in textual criticism. Davis retired from Oxford in 1960.
During his academic career, Davis made several notable contributions. Following his passion for poetry and prose, Davis became a world renowned expert on Jonathan Swift and wrote several books on his work including Swift's View of Poetry (1931) and Stella, a Gentlewoman of the Eighteenth Century (1942). The latter is an account of the friendship that existed between Swift and Esther Johnson. Davis also edited the fourteen volume work, The Prose Works of Jonathan Swift (1939-68). Davis' distinguished literary contributions were well recognized and he received several honorary degrees including a Doctorate of Laws from Amherst College in 1940.
In addition to his enthusiasm for the English language, Davis was also extremely socially conscious and particularly concerned with WWII raging overseas. Perhaps his most memorable act of charity was providing a home to five British refugee children for several years during the war. Many of his colleagues and friends followed his lead and opened their doors to children in need. Davis died on March 28, 1967.
1893 Born on May 24, at Long Buckby, Northamponshire, England. Son of Carter and Martha Ann (Sheldon) Davis.
1905 Educated at Northampton Grammar School.
1911 St. John's College, Oxford.
1912 Pass Moderations (Classics)
1914 B.A.; Honour School of English Language and Literature.
1915 Reading for Anglican Orders, Wells Theological College.
1916-1919 War Service--gunner, R.G.A.; subaltern with 301 Siege Battery, France and Belgium; acting-adjutant, 4th Brigade, R.G.A., Army of Occupation.
1919 M.A., Oxford.
1920 Lecturer in English, University of Leeds.
1922 Associate Professor English, University College, Toronto. Married Gertrude Lucas of Opladen, Rheinland, Germany.
1924-1925 Guest Professor in the University of Cologne, Germany.
1925-1935 Professor of English, University College, Toronto. Elected Chairman of the Department of English, University of Toronto.
1928 Gertrude Lucas Davis died.
1930 Married Gladys Wookey of Toronto. Children--Charlotte Elisabeth Ann Davis (Falconer) and Jane Davis (Knowles).
1937 Appointed Professor of English at Cornell University; granted leave of absence for one year in England. Frederic Ives Carpenter Visiting Professor at the University of Chicago, summer quarter.
1938 Chairman of the Department of English, Cornell University.
1939 Appointed Goldwin Smith Professor of English Literature at Cornell University.
1940 Accepts position as fourth President of Smith College; L.L.D. from Amherst College.
1949 Leaves Smith College; Returns to Oxford to teach English.
1960 Retires from Oxford.
1967 March 28, 1967--Died.
1893 Born on May 24, at Long Buckby, Northamponshire, England. Son of Carter and Martha Ann (Sheldon) Davis.
1905 Educated at Northampton Grammar School.
1911 St. John's College, Oxford.
1912 Pass Moderations (Classics)
1914 B.A.; Honour School of English Language and Literature.
1915 Reading for Anglican Orders, Wells Theological College.
1916-1919 War Service--gunner, R.G.A.; subaltern with 301 Siege Battery, France and Belgium; acting-adjutant, 4th Brigade, R.G.A., Army of Occupation.
1919 M.A., Oxford.
1920 Lecturer in English, University of Leeds.
1922 Associate Professor English, University College, Toronto. Married Gertrude Lucas of Opladen, Rheinland, Germany.
1924-1925 Guest Professor in the University of Cologne, Germany.
1925-1935 Professor of English, University College, Toronto. Elected Chairman of the Department of English, University of Toronto.
1928 Gertrude Lucas Davis died.
1930 Married Gladys Wookey of Toronto. Children--Charlotte Elisabeth Ann Davis (Falconer) and Jane Davis (Knowles).
1937 Appointed Professor of English at Cornell University; granted leave of absence for one year in England. Frederic Ives Carpenter Visiting Professor at the University of Chicago, summer quarter.
1938 Chairman of the Department of English, Cornell University.
1939 Appointed Goldwin Smith Professor of English Literature at Cornell University.
1940 Accepts position as fourth President of Smith College; L.L.D. from Amherst College.
1949 Leaves Smith College; Returns to Oxford to teach English.
1960 Retires from Oxford.
1967 March 28, 1967--Died.
Scope and Contents
The Herbert John Davis Personal Papers are primarily related to his personal life. Types of material include correspondence; speeches; publications; photographs; newspaper articles; and memorabilia. Although the chronological focus of the collection is Davis' presidential years, the records pertain to life outside his presidential duties.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence
III. Inauguration
IV. Photographs
V. Publications and Speeches
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers were transferred to the College Archives from the Office of the President after President Davis left the College in 1949.
Smith College -- presidents; Davis, Herbert John, 1893-1967.; Swift, Jonathan, 1667-1745.; Smith College--Presidents.
- Series I. Biographical Material, 1893-1973; 2.5 linear inches
  Scope and Contents
  This series provides an overview of Herbert John Davis' career and personal life and is arranged alphabetically. Newspaper clippings and magazine articles, dating from 1939 to 1973, document Davis' many achievements, focusing on education, awards, and travel as well as his work with the European Recovery Program.
  - Association of Begatees of Clergymen, undated (Box 448, Folder 1)
  - Awards, 1940-1947; undated (Box 448, Folder 2)
  - Data, 1893-1973 (Box 448, Folder 3)
  - Degrees, 1940-1949; 1957 (Box 448, Folder 4)
  - European Recovery Program, 1948 (Box 448, Folder 5)
  - Luncheons, etc., 1947 (Box 448, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1941 (Box 448, Folder 7)
  - Newsclippings and Publications, Oct 1944-Dec 1946 (Box 448, Folder 8)
  - Obituaries, 1967 (Box 448, Folder 9)
  - Resignation, 1948; undated (Box 448, Folder 10)
  - Resignation - Surprise Party, 1949 (Box 448, Folder 11)
  - Trips Abroad, 1946-1948 (Box 448, Folder 12)
- Series II. Correspondence, 1940-1950; 5 linear inches
  This series documents Davis' personal correspondence during his time as president of Smith College. This series is arranged by subject and includes correspondence regarding, among other things, Davis' interest in the author Jonathan Swift.
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1948 (Box 448, Folder 13)
  - The Atheneum Pall Mall, 1948 (Box 448, Folder 14)
  - Birch Wathen School, 1945 (Box 448, Folder 15)
  - British Consulate, 1942, 1944 (Box 448, Folder 16)
  - British Refugee Children, 1940-1942 (Box 448, Folder 17)
    - Sponsors-Davis, Herbert J., 1940-1943 (Box 448, Folder 18)
    - Sponsors, A-L, 1940-1941 (Box 448, Folder 19)
    - Sponsors, M-Z, 1940-1943 (Box 448, Folder 20)
  - Connely, Willard, Jul 1940-Mar 1941 (Box 448, Folder 21)
  - Davis, Gertrude, Fellowship, 1947-1950 (Box 448, Folder 22)
  - Finn, John, 1949-1950 (Box 448, Folder 23)
  - Grolier Club, 1949 (Box 448, Folder 24)
  - Homberg, May 1949 (Box 448, Folder 25)
  - Invitations, 1940 (Box 448, Folder 26)
  - Johnson, Oct 1949-Jan 1950 (Box 448, Folder 27)
  - Kinnevan, J.W., 1942-1943 (Box 448, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous, 1942-1950 (Box 448, Folder 29)
  - Mongan, 1941 (Box 448, Folder 30)
  - New Modern Language Association, 1941 (Box 448, Folder 31)
  - Oxford, England, 1948 (Box 448, Folder 32)
  - Pons, 1949 (Box 448, Folder 33)
  - Power, Eugene, 1941 (Box 448, Folder 34)
  - Randall, 1949-1950 (Box 448, Folder 35)
  - Resignation
    - Responses, A-L, 1948 (Box 449, Folder 1)
    - Responses, M-Z, 1948 (Box 449, Folder 2)
  - Smith, Anne Nichol, 1943-1944 (Box 449, Folder 3)
  - Smith, David Nichol, 1940; 1944 (Box 449, Folder 4)
  - Schroder, August, 1948-1949 (Box 449, Folder 5)
  - Schott, Carl, 1948-1949 (Box 449, Folder 6)
  - Spect, Betty, 1949 (Box 449, Folder 7)
  - Swift, Jonathan
    - 1939-1940 (Box 449, Folder 8)
    - July 1, 1940-July 1, 1942 (Box 449, Folder 9)
    - July 1, 1942-July 1, 1944 (Box 449, Folder 10)
    - July 1, 1944-July 1, 1945 (Box 449, Folder 11)
    - July 1, 1945-July 1, 1946 (Box 449, Folder 12)
    - July 1, 1946-July 1, 1947 (Box 449, Folder 13)
    - July 1, 1947-July 1, 1948 (Box 449, Folder 14)
    - July 1, 1948-July 1, 1949 (Box 449, Folder 15)
    - Index to Vol. XI (Box 449, Folder 16)
  - "War and Post War", 1942 (Box 449, Folder 17)
  - Wooley, David, 1949 (Box 449, Folder 18)
  - Yale University, 1944-1949 (Box 449, Folder 19)
- Series III. Inauguration, 1939-1940; 2.5 linear inches
  This series documents Davis' presidential appointment in 1939 as well as his inauguration in 1940. Included in this series are congratulatory letters from colleagues and friends as well as newspaper clippings and publications.
  - Appointment and Pre-Inaugural Visit, 1939-1940 (Box 449, Folder 20)
  - Committee of Inauguration, 1940 (Box 449, Folder 21)
  - Congratulations, Nov 1939-Jul 1940 (Box 449, Folder 22)
  - Congratulations, Alumnae and Smith College Clubs, 1940 (Box 450, Folder 1)
  - Exercises, 1940 (Box 450, Folder 2)
  - Luncheon and Broadcast, 1940 (Box 450, Folder 3)
  - Newsclippings and Publications
    - Appointment, 1939 (Box 450, Folder 4)
    - Inauguration, 1940 (Box 450, Folder 5)
- Series IV. Photographs, 1939-1964; 2.5 linear inches
  The bulk of this series documents Davis' presidency at Smith College and is arranged chornologically. Included in this series are inaugural photographs, formal portraits, candid shots, and the weddings of daughters, Charlotte Elisabeth Ann Davis (Falconer) and Jane Davis (Knowles).
  - 1939-1940 (Box 450, Folder 6)
  - Inauguration, Oct 1940 (Box 450, Folder 7)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 450, Folder 8)
  - British Children, 1940-1941 (Box 450, Folder 9)
  - President and Mrs. Davis, 1940-1941 (Box 450, Folder 10)
  - 1942-1943 (Box 450, Folder 11)
  - 1945-1946 (Box 450, Folder 12)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 450, Folder 13)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 450, Folder 14)
  - Formal, 1940-1949 (Box 450, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940-1949 (Box 450, Folder 16)
  - The weddings of Charlotte Elizabeth Ann Davis (Falconer)and Jane Davis (Knowles), 1957-1964 (Box 450, Folder 17)
- Series V. Publications and Speeches, 1940-1964; 1.5 linear feet
  Arrangement
  Arranged by subject.
  This series is comprised of speeches and publications written during Davis' presidency at Smith College and the years following. Included are speeches given at area colleges and organizations and his published work on the poetry of Jonathan Swift.
  - Publications
    - Untitled, 1941-49 (Box 451, Folder 1)
    - American Association of University Professors, undated (Box 451, Folder 2)
    - Article for Professor Lowenstein, 1941 (Box 451, Folder 3)
    - Burden of Knowledge, 1945 (Box 451, Folder 4)
    - Challenge to the Intellect, 1941 (Box 451, Folder 5)
    - Charles Montagu Doughty, 1945 (Box 451, Folder 6)
    - Foreign Literatures and Our Youth, 1941 (Box 451, Folder 7)
    - Freshman Handbook, 1948 (Box 451, Folder 8)
    - Inaugural Speeches, 1940 (Box 451, Folder 9)
    - The Manuscripts of Swift's "directions to servants", 1954 (Box 451, Folder 10)
    - No Time for Poetry, 1941 (Box 451, Folder 11)
    - The Poetry of Jonathan Swift, 1939-1941 (Box 451, Folder 12)
    - Princeton University, 1944-1947 (Box 451, Folder 13)
    - Princeton University-Awards, 1946 (Box 451, Folder 14)
    - Recent Studies of Swift and Johnson, 1959 (Box 451, Folder 15)
    - Reviews, 1942-1945 (Box 451, Folder 16)
    - Satire of Jonathan Swift, 1939-1947 (Box 451, Folder 17)
    - Smith Alumnae Quarterly, 1944; undated (Box 451, Folder 18)
    - Smith College Museum of Art, 1959 (Box 451, Folder 19)
    - Stella, 1942 (Box 451, Folder 20)
    - WAVES, 1942-1943 (Box 452, Folder 1)
    - Wilson, Frank Percy, 1963 (Box 452, Folder 2)
  - Speeches
    - Advice to Daughters, undated (Box 452, Folder 3)
    - Alumnae Association, 14 Jun 1941 (Box 452, Folder 4)
    - Alumnae College, 1941 (Box 452, Folder 5)
    - Alumnae Council, 1941-1949 (Box 452, Folder 6)
    - American College Publicity Association, 1944 (Box 452, Folder 7)
    - American Russian Institute Dinner, 1948 (Box 452, Folder 8)
    - Amherst College, 1940 (Box 452, Folder 9)
    - Ann Arbor, 3 Oct 1946 (Box 452, Folder 10)
    - Armistice Day, 1940 (Box 452, Folder 11)
    - Assembly, 1939-1949 (Box 452, Folder 12)
    - Assembly, 10 Dec 1947 (Box 452, Folder 13)
    - Augustan Art of Conversation, 1957 (Box 452, Folder 14)
    - Baccalaureate, 1941-1949 (Box 452, Folder 15)
    - Bates College, 1946 (Box 452, Folder 16)
    - Boston, 1940 (Box 452, Folder 17)
    - Brown University, 1941 (Box 452, Folder 18)
    - Chapel Talks, Sep 1940-Jan 1943 (Box 452, Folder 19)
    - Chapel Talks, Sep 1943-Jun 1949 (Box 452, Folder 20)
    - Christmas Celebration, 1942 (Box 452, Folder 21)
    - Commencement, Smith College, 1943 (Box 452, Folder 22)
    - Commencement, Smith College, 1944 (Box 452, Folder 23)
    - Commencement, Smith College, 1950 (Box 452, Folder 24)
    - Conference on Academic Freedom, 1948 (Box 452, Folder 25)
    - Conference on Academic Freedom, 1949-1950 (Box 452, Folder 26)
    - Conference on Education about the Soviet Union, 1944 (Box 452, Folder 27)
    - Connecticut College, 1941-1947 (Box 452, Folder 28)
    - Cooley Dickenson Hospital, undated (Box 452, Folder 29)
    - Criticism of Writer's Manifesto in Horizon, undated (Box 452, Folder 30)
    - Democracy, undated (Box 452, Folder 31)
    - Education at Smith College, New York, 1947; undated (Box 452, Folder 32)
    - Eighteenth Century Conference, 1947 (Box 452, Folder 33)
    - England, undated (Box 452, Folder 34)
    - Ethel Walker School, undated (Box 452, Folder 35)
    - Faculty Meetings, 1940-1947; undated (Box 452, Folder 36)
    - Freedom in Education, undated (Box 452, Folder 37)
    - Gaucher College, 1949-1956 (Box 452, Folder 38)
    - Grolier Club Dinner, 1945 (Box 452, Folder 39)
    - Humanities and a Liberal Arts Education, undated (Box 453, Folder 1)
    - Inaugural, 1940 (Box 453, Folder 2)
    - Jefferson Day, 1945 (Box 453, Folder 3)
    - Kent Place School, 1945 (Box 453, Folder 4)
    - Kiwanis, 1949 (Box 453, Folder 5)
    - Limits of General Education, 1947 (Box 453, Folder 6)
    - Literature, Teaching of, undated (Box 453, Folder 7)
    - Massachusetts State College, 1944 (Box 453, Folder 8)
    - Mt. Holyoke College, 1941-1949 (Box 453, Folder 9)
    - New Concepts in Education for Women, 1945 (Box 453, Folder 10)
    - New York Dinner, 30 Apr 1946 (Box 453, Folder 11)
    - New York, Executive Committee, 10 Apr 1947 (Box 453, Folder 12)
    - New York Luncheon, 1943 (Box 453, Folder 13)
    - New York Smith College Club, 1948 (Box 453, Folder 14)
    - Northampton Chamber of Commerce, 1940 (Box 453, Folder 15)
    - Northampton Grammar School, 1952 (Box 453, Folder 16)
    - Northampton Historical Society, 1946 (Box 453, Folder 17)
    - Northfield School for Girls, 1942 (Box 453, Folder 18)
    - Phi Beta Kappa, 1949 (Box 453, Folder 19)
    - Poland, 1941 (Box 453, Folder 20)
    - Pompeian Conference, 1948 (Box 453, Folder 21)
    - Pontypool Girls' School, 1951 (Box 453, Folder 22)
    - Princeton University, 1941 (Box 453, Folder 23)
    - Queen's University, 1945 (Box 453, Folder 24)
    - Radio Broadcasts, 1942; undated (Box 453, Folder 25)
    - Rally Day
      General
      See: Washington's Birthday Introductions
    - Rhodes House, 1954 (Box 453, Folder 26)
    - Scholarships, undated (Box 453, Folder 27)
    - Scripps College, 1964 (Box 453, Folder 28)
    - Senior Day, 1943 (Box 453, Folder 29)
    - Smith Clubs, 1941-1949 (Box 453, Folder 30)
    - Summer Session, 1943; 1944 (Box 453, Folder 31)
    - Sweet Briar College, 1943 (Box 453, Folder 32)
    - Toronto University-Alexander Lectures, 1942 (Box 453, Folder 33)
    - Trustee-Faculty Dinner, 1944 (Box 453, Folder 34)
    - Trustee's Meetings, 1948 (Box 453, Folder 35)
    - Unidentified, 1940; 1948; 1949; undated (Box 453, Folder 36)
    - V-E Day Plan, 1945 (Box 453, Folder 37)
    - Vespers, 1940-1948 (Box 453, Folder 38)
    - Washington's Birthday Introductions, 1941-1949 (Box 453, Folder 39)
    - WAVES, 1942; 1944 (Box 453, Folder 40)
    - Wells College, undated (Box 453, Folder 41)
    - Wheaton College, 1942 (Box 453, Folder 42)
    - Williamsburg-175th Anniversary, 1946 (Box 453, Folder 43)
    - Williston Academy, undated (Box 453, Folder 44)
    - Wilson College, 1945 (Box 453, Folder 45)
    - Yale University Lecture, 1942; 1944 (Box 453, Folder 46)